In this lesson, we're going to talk about generic interfaces and generic classes in TypeScript.
Generics allow us to write reusable, flexible, and type-safe code.
And it's heavily used in real-world TypeScript projects and frameworks.
If you want to have functions like array, IT, or libraries like Angular and React,
stay flexible while remaining type-safe, this is how.
Let's start with a common problem, suppose you want to store values of different types,
but we still want TypeScript to help us with type-safety.
So for example, if we have function and then identity, and say value any, then return value,
this works, but using the any removes or type-safety, TypeScript cannot be able to help us anymore.
We want flexibility without losing type information.
That's where generics come in.
So a generic is a placeholder for a type.
Instead of hard-coding a specific type, we use a type variable, commonly called T.
generics let us write code at the works of many types while still preserving strong typing.
So let's now change this function to use some generics.
So we're going to change where we have value here to T.
First of all, we need to define exactly what T is.
We don't know what T is, but we can do it as generic T
by doing an angle brackets here just after the function, we put T.
So now in TypeScript happy because we define what T is.
But we need to then use this function for TypeScript to know exactly what this type is going to be.
I'm not going to show you how that works in just a moment.
Maybe we want this function to return a type of the same type that we've actually sent in.
We can do that by doing code on and then T.
So this looks a bit strange.
Let's see how this works in practice.
If we do const and say number value, we can call this function identity
and let's say we want to work with numbers.
So we then do it in angle brackets and say number.
Then we can call our function and notice now that TypeScript is prompting us
to supply a number or a value of type number.
So it's now used the number that we have specified here, matched it with the type T.
And now this is expecting type T, which in this case is number, to be supplied to us.
We can now do, for example, 10 then to a colon.
And then this function is then going to return us a type, a number type.
If we then try and change this value 10 to something that's not a number, let's say a string,
it's then going to complain because it's expecting us to supply a number.
Let's just change it back to 10.
But we can then call the function again and change the actual type again.
So we can do const and say string value equals identity.
This time we're going to work with strings to put strings in angle brackets.
Now if we try and provide a 10, it's not going to let us because it's expecting us to supply a parameter of string.
We can now do, for example, hello, and that's going to be accepted.
And of course we could do the same for any other type.
Now TypeScript knows the exact return type, so no use of any and no guessing.
Now with generics, TypeScript's going to keep track of the type for us,
whereas using the any keyword, it doesn't.
This is where generics are safer, and preferred when using professional code bases.
Now let's move on from functions to generic interfaces.
I'm going to remove this here.
Let's define a new interface.
Let's say let's say, for example, API response, a very common use for generics.
We then provide a type T. Now we can start to find our interface.
We're going to have a data method or data property.
This is going to be our type T.
Don't know at this point, then have a colon.
And now we want the status.
The status we're going to have as a number, for example, 200 or maybe 404.
So this interface represents a generic API response.
The data property can be of any type.
So perhaps, for example, you could have a customer or maybe a product,
or maybe lack of category.
So let's do a couple examples into a const user response.
This is going to be our type API response, and in our particular API for the user response,
we're going to just return a string.
So I'm going to put a string in here.
Now we can define the actual members.
So we can see data.
And if we try and do a number, it's going to start to complain because it's expecting a string.
So in our data, we're going to return Alice.
And then the status we're going to set to 200.
And now we can use this response again into const product response.
I'll type API response, and this is going to expect a number equals our data.
It has to be a number, we put number in here, and our status again could be 200.
So the same interface works for different data types while remaining type safe.
This pattern is extremely common when dealing with APIs, as we can see.
It can be also very useful with classes.
So let's do a class here.
Let's do class and say storage.
Let's put our generics in here.
Now we're going to create some items, so private items.
The items are going to be an array of a generic type.
So we do t and then to square brackets.
Let's initialize that array like this.
Okay, so we have items.
Now we can define a method to add.
We want to supply an item of type T.
The app method is going to return nothing, so we put void.
And now we can put the implementation, which is going to be this dot items.
Whoosh.
App type T, so pushing our item.
We can now do another method.
For example, get all.
We're going to return an array of our type T.
Now we do is return this dot items.
Everyone doing what this error is.
It's because this storage just happens to be a duplicate identifier,
use on this website.
So I'm going to change this to something like my storage.
That's just going to change, get rid of the error message.
This class can store any type, but once the type is chosen,
it's then enforced everywhere.
Let's assign some examples, so we can do const string storage.
This new my storage, and we can just store some strings.
Now we can do string storage at.
Add some string events, say apples.
Then we can do string storage, get all.
Then we can reuse this again into number storage equals new my storage.
This time it's going to store some numbers.
The number storage adds, let's give it a value, say 10.
Then we can call our method again.
Each instance is locked up a particular type,
and TypeScripts can provide prevent mixing types.
Now sometimes we want a generic, but we have rules.
This is where we're talking about generic constraints.
For example, if we do function, let's do log length,
and what type of type T.
This time it's going to extend this type,
so we're going to now define the type we want to extend.
Let's say we have length property of type number.
To finish off the definition,
we want to supply a value, so a value is going to be a type T,
and the function is then going to return void.
So this is looking, starting to look a little bit more complicated,
but hopefully you can understand what we're doing here.
Now we can do console, log, value, dot length.
So what's this doing? Well, it's ensuring that our type T must have a length property.
So now we can do, for example, log length.
We can say hello.
Let's execute this.
We get a value of fire over here, this is making a big bigger.
We turn the string to, like, hello world.
Execute this.
We get a value of 11.
Let's do another use into log length,
and this time we're going to supply an array,
1, 2, 3, 4 and 5. Let's execute that, and we get a value of 5,
and let's just remove this one, stop us getting confused.
Let's just clear the console.
And now run.
We get a value of 5 here, and of course we change the value of,
I rent length of the array, maybe six and four, it run, we then get seven.
So when should we use generics?
So use generics when we want to use reasonable code.
We want flexibility without any.
We want the input and output types to be related,
and maybe you might be building utilities or libraries.